<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short account of what was deposed; together with the names of several of the persons, that experimented Mr. Warner's earth, and gave evidence for the King at the late tryal at barr in the Court of Exchequer, which was had by order of Their Majesties in Council, upon the petition of many hundred of clothyers, fullers, clothworkers and others relating to the wollen manufacture: the 24th. Novemb. 1693.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B29771</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885122</idno>
  <idno type="VID">185580</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264214630</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3545</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.14[127]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.12[103]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220760</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885122</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99885122e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B29771)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C1:3[127]; C19:1[103])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short account of what was deposed; together with the names of several of the persons, that experimented Mr. Warner's earth, and gave evidence for the King at the late tryal at barr in the Court of Exchequer, which was had by order of Their Majesties in Council, upon the petition of many hundred of clothyers, fullers, clothworkers and others relating to the wollen manufacture: the 24th. Novemb. 1693.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Warner, Edmund --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fuller's earth --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Clothing and trade --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Wool industry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:185580:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185580:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A short Account of what was Deposed; together with the Names of several of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, that Experimented Mr.</hi> Warner's <hi>Earth, and gave Evidence for the</hi> King <hi>at the late Tryal at Barr in the Court of</hi> Exchequer, <hi>which was bad by Order of Their Majesties in Council, upon the Petition of many Hundred of</hi> Clothyers, Fullers, Clothworkers <hi>and others relating to the</hi> Wollen Manufacture: <hi>The</hi> 24<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. Novemb. 1693.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>From the</hi> Banck-side, Southwark.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Jer. Warberton, <hi>Millman;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tho. Clare, <hi>Clothworker,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>SWORE they had Experimented the Earth, which they fetched them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from the King's Ware-house, that it was good Fullers Earth, and they had used no other since <hi>May</hi> last, and had Scowred above 100 Cloths, and fetch'd out Sally Spots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the same.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the City of</hi> Worcester.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Tho. Crundal <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>Merchent;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fra. Chetle, <hi>Clothyer of</hi> Worcester;</item>
               <item>Edward Stanton, <hi>of</hi> London <hi>Cittizen;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Clothyers.
<list>
                     <item>John Burton, <hi>Maj.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Tho. Reynalds,</item>
                     <item>Rich Hill,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fullers.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Pinson Wilmot,</item>
                     <item>William Brewer,</item>
                     <item>John Crump,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Upon several Petitons to the Queen in Council from divers Counties, Signed by many Hundred <hi>Clothyers,</hi> and others relating to the Wollen Manufacture; Praying, the Earth in Question being Good Fullers Earth might be Prosecuted, and not suffered to be Exported <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It came Referred to the Commissioners of the Customs, who to know the Truth of the Matter, desired Mr. <hi>Crundal,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chetley,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Stanton,</hi> before Named, who themselves took the Earth out of the King's Ware-house, to go with it to the City of <hi>Worcester;</hi> Where, in the Presence of the said Persons together with the Mayor, and several other Clothyers and Fullers here mentioned, the said Earth was Experiment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Three several Cloths, and the said Persons appearing at the Tryal, Testified that the said Earth without mixture, did all the Offices of other good Fullers Earth, and produced Two Cloths in Court Fulled with the said Earth, being perfectly Made, and Good Cloth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From</hi> Sommerset-shire.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Nat. Stiles, <hi>Clothyer fetched the said Earth from the Custom-House and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry'd it down.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Samuel Blindman, <hi>Fuller.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>These brought a White Cloth Fulled with the said Earth, and Swore it to be good Fullers Earth, and that it did all the Offices as other Fullers Earth perfectly and well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From</hi> Godallming <hi>in</hi> Surrey.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clothyers fetched the Earth from the Kings Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house;</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Law. Collins,</item>
                     <item>Hen. Bowler,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clothyers.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>John Toft, <hi>Sei.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>John Toft, <hi>Jun.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Will. Shrub.</item>
                     <item>John Shrub,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fullers.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Will. Perryer,</item>
                     <item>George Wood,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>These gave Evidence that the Earth of Mr. <hi>Warner</hi> which they had often Try'd, was good Fullers Earth, and did all the Offices of such Earth, being a better sort then that used commonly by them; and produced One Cloth, and One Kerzey in Court Fulled with the said Earth without any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and that the said Cloths were good Cloths perfectly made; at the same time also brought in Court a Cloth Raw and in the Greace from the Loom, that the Court mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht be Sensible of its Opperation, which Stunk so of the Greace that it could not be Endured in Court, and they all Swore that the Cloths that were Fulled by the Earth in Question, were before as Foul as the said Stinking Cloth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From</hi> Reading <hi>in</hi> Berks.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fetch'd the Earth from the King's</hi> Ware-house.
<list>
                     <item>J. Wilmot, <hi>Clothyer;</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Nat. Collins, <hi>Fuller;</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clothyers.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Edward Froome,</item>
                     <item>William Horne,</item>
                     <item>William May,</item>
                     <item>John Silvester,</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>These Deposed that the Earth in Question was good Fullers Earth, and better then the sort of that Country; that it perform'd all the Offices of good Fullers Earth, and brought a Cloth in Court Worked with the said Earth, which they Depos'd was a perfect and good Cloth; and that the said Earth was as good as any Earth they ever Used.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Case being thought to be sufficiently Proved, no more Evidence was offered for the King, altho several others were in Court, from</hi> Wiltshire, Glocester, Essex, <hi>and many other Places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Prosecutors for the King before the Tryal made several motions in Court, that the Barons would be pleased to direct the Place and Persons, where a Joynt Experiment might be made, and all Parties present, that the Court might come to a true Knowledge of a Case of this Consequence; and to prevent opposite Sweareing, which was always refused by Mr.</hi> Warner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So the Evidence being Contradictory upon Experiments made on behalf of the Defena▪ and Scowring Earth being only mentioned in the Title, but not in the Body of the Act; The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> brought in a Verdict for the Defendant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:185580:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185580:2"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>